Today, today's דף Daf is חודש טוב. Chodesh Tov. Today's כ' Kaf
דף Daf is י"ח Yud-Chet חי Chai סוטה. Sotah. And we pick
up about five lines down from the top of י"ח עמוד א'
Yud-Chet Amud Aleph בעי רבא. Ba'ei Rava. So we're dealing with the
act of scraping the curses into the water. We discussed the collection
of the water, a little bit about the nature of the vessel.
We discussed the what was written on the scroll, which sections were
written and what the scroll had to be made out of. The
משנה Mishnah also mentioned what the ink had to be made out
of
and the גמרא Gemara discussed other parts about the physical nature of
the scroll of the writing. It couldn't you can't write it backwards.
The scroll has to be scored. It has to be one piece
of parchment, not two pieces of parchment and so on. And with
that we continue the following בעי רבא. Ba'ei Rava. So רבא Rava
asked Are we in the משנה? Mishnah? We're not in the משנה.
Mishnah. No. עמוד א' Amud Aleph of
י"ח. Yud-Chet. No. בעי רבא כתב שתי מגילות לשתי סוטות. Ba'ei Rava
katav shtei megillot lishtei sotot. Or
let's say you wrote two מגילות megillot for two סוטות. sotot. You
were doing you know you were just processing things quickly there so
you did two you were doing two at the same time ומחקן
לתוך כוס אחד umachakan letoch kos echad
and you scraped them all into the same single vessel.
So can they both drink from the water of one vessel of
one vessel that has in it the two מגילות. megillot. So what
do we say מהו? mahu? What's the הלכה? halacha? כתיבה לשמה בעינן.
ketivah lishmah be'inan. It has to be written the presumed that you
don't have a pre-written text right that it's written specifically וכתב לה
הכהן vechatav lah hakohen right so you write her for her. I
mean before we spoke about you know that you can't that you
can't write it like before she takes the oath you have to
write it after she takes the oath. So it's very specifically written
at that time and it's written לה lah for her. So that
you did איכא ika מגילה megillah was written for each woman individually
so בעינן ואיכא be'inan ve'ika you have that או דילמא בעינן נמי
מחיקה לשמה o dilma be'inan nami mechika lishmah or maybe it has
to be scraped for their name. Now it was scraped for the
name. You were scraping one for שרה Sarah and then you took
the other one and you scraped it for רחל. Rachel. But presumably
what it means is that the scrape that it has to be
actually being done like not just in your mind for that person
but it has to be sort of like seen as you know
that like like by the action it's specific to that person. It's
and therefore when you're scraping it if you're scraping two at the
same time I mean I guess if you did רחל Rachel first
and then לאה Leah maybe we could say רחל Rachel was good
and לאה Leah wasn't. But let's say you were actually somehow scraping
them both at the same time then the act of scraping wasn't
individualized for a particular person. Yeah it's true when your knife went
on רחל's Rachel's parchment it was for רחל Rachel and went on
לאה's Leah's parchment it was for לאה Leah but the whole sort
of process if you would of scraping it and making the water
the process of making the water by the scraping was not individualized
for this woman as opposed to for that woman. This was a
water that was now being made for two women and maybe that's
a problem. Maybe it has to be individualized. You have a discussion
the other day but there's nothing individualized about this document. There's nothing
in the text that's
individualized but the גמרא Gemara is assuming that the idea of לשמה
lishmah at least describes you know somewhat your intent and to some
degree that by context the action has to be focused you know
on this woman. So here here if it's you know this was
written for you and this was written for the other woman and
we're scraping it at the so the act of writing was seen
as based on your intention but I mean I guess the woman
doesn't have to be the כהן kohen could be not looking at
the woman while he's writing it. So it's true like how much
is it what's going on in his head and how much of
it is like somehow defined by the context of the actions. But
there is a sense that the וכתב לה vechatav lah has to
be specific for her and the question is does the scraping you
know now the process of making the water it's being done simultaneously
for for two women at the same time. It's a water for
for two women. Is that good or not? Yeah. So you have
a כוס kos with water and soil in it and you're scraping
ink into it. Right. And she's drinking that. Right. So the power
ostensibly comes from the name of God floating around through the scraped
ink. Presumably. I mean or the whole curse. The whole curse. I
don't know if it's just the name of God. The גמרא Gemara
emphasizes the name of God because that's why it's so powerful that
we're prepared to erase God's name but presumably it's the presence of
the whole curse in there that gives it that that power. And
who makes the mixture? The כהן kohen makes the mixture of the
water. The כהן kohen makes the mixture of the water. Yeah. And
he can mix the water all different things different he can
mix lighter. Yeah. He can decide how much dirt to put in
or whatever what exactly the mixture. In this case they don't give
a שיעור. shiur. Well yeah that's true. Yeah. Depends on the woman.
Well I don't know if that would affect whether the water would
have the effect or not but maybe he could decide how much
dirt to put in or whatever that'd be true. They don't give
a שיעור shiur here. What? They don't give a שיעור shiur for
the dirt. That's true. Oh well it does. It says it has
to be enough dirt that it floats on the top but it
doesn't give a maximum or whatever. Yeah.
Yeah, that you wind up drinking another woman's scrapings. So the גמרא
Gemorah is going to get to that. That'll be the next level
question. Right, you could also ask like, wouldn't it be interesting if
the same water like worked for one woman and didn't work for
another, because one woman was innocent and the other woman was guilty?
So, you know, so do you have like the power of this
name here for one? It's like the presence of the scraping is
going to cleanse ונקתה ונזרעה v'niktah v'nizra'ah and the other is going
to curse or whatever? Can that both exist simultaneously in the same
water? So anyway, but right now we're not even up to that.
We're just about the act of scraping has to be individualized. Okay?
Can it exist simultaneously in the same water for the same one
woman? Only one woman, still the same... yes, but then, but then
it is going to do just one thing. Here the water is
going to do two different things, you know? Potentially. Yeah, well that's
true. Okay.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemorah says like this. Okay, so what's the
הלכה? halacha? ואם תמצא לומר בעינן נמי מחיקה לשמה, v'im timtzei lomar
bayinan nami mechika lishmah, the scraping has to be like individualized for
that woman. ומחקם בבי כוסות, u'mechakam b'vei kossos,
okay fine, so you did each woman, you wrote her מגילה megillah
and you scraped it into a vessel and you had a separate
vessel for each woman too. Right, it never asked that the gathering
of the dirt has to be for the woman anyway, but you
created the potion as it were, individual... two separate potions for two
separate women. And
then חזר ועירבן מהו? chazar v'irvan mahu? Now you mixed the waters
together. So the act of the כתב ktav and מחה, macha, all
of that was proper, but now the question is just the resultant
water itself is both waters. Is that going to be a problem?
The process was okay, but the water might be a problem because
it's not just that one woman's water.
So what's the question? ואם תמצא לומר חזר ועירבן מהו? v'im timtzei
lomar chazar v'irvan mahu? מחיקה לשמה
בעינן ואיכא, mechika lishmah bayinan v'ika, you need scraping and you did
it for that individualized... או דילמא האי לאו דידה קא שתיא והאי
לאו דידה קא שתיא, o dilma hai lav didah ka shatya v'hai
lav didah ka shatya, each woman is drinking water that isn't hers
and maybe that's a problem, right? That you only... that the actual
drinking has to be just the water that was prepared for you.
ואם תמצא לומר האי לאו דידה קא שתיא והאי לאו דידה קא
שתיא, v'im timtzei lomar hai lav didah ka shatya v'hai lav didah
ka shatya, that's a problem because each woman is drinking water that
was not specifically prepared for them and might even have a different
power based on the other woman, חזר וחילקן מהו? chazar v'chilkan mahu?
Let's say after you mixed the waters together, now you divided them
again. Okay, mixed them into two cups, you sort of did like
a שבע ברכות sheva brachot thing
exactly. Mixed them into two cups and then you separated them out,
מהו? mahu? יש ברירה yesh breira או אין ברירה? o ein breira?
Do we say that the thing sort of selects itself out or
not? תיקו, teiku, we don't know. Now the last question is a
little bit bizarre because as תוספות Tosafot discusses, one of these long
תוספות, Tosafot, a normal יש ברירה yesh breira is something where you
don't have to say that by magic something, you know, actually cell
out exactly the way we had... you know, you had two distinct
things were mixed together and somehow we're going to say by pure
magic, I mean how is it supposed to work that way? That
they re-separate exactly the way that they had initially been? Like, you
know, תוספות Tosafot asks like, then if you could say that, why
would you ever have a case of תערובת? taarovet? Let's say you
got your, you know, let's say you got your תרומה terumah grain
mixed in with your, I don't know, your תרומה terumah wine mixed
in with your חולין chullin wine and you are... and they got
all mixed up. He says, oh no problem, let me just let
me just, you know, spill out to two separate vessels and I'll
say the תרומה terumah wine went into that vessel. Like, like it's
crazy. How could ever such a thing ever happen? You know, I
mean obviously something fully diffuses and how, you know, we never would
say such a thing. Normally when we say יש ברירה, yesh breira,
it's the following type of an example. When we say יש ברירה,
yesh breira, it's a scenario where the thing had not been as
תוספות Tosafot said, it was never ניכר מתחילה. nikar mitchilah. It was
never initially labeled and then got mixed up. It had never been
labeled at the outset. So for example, let's say I were to
say,
the grain that I will eventually take from this pile will be
תרומה terumah as of now. And then, you know, tomorrow I take
the grain. Then we say well retroactively that was always the grain
that was תרומה. terumah. Or maybe there's even a better example. There
I stipulated so you could say it's a type of a תנאי.
tnai. Let's say a case where I didn't stipulate. Let's say a
case where we jointly own a field. Do we say that when
I walk through the field at that time that I'm walking through
it, like I'm using my portion of the field? Like, you know,
it's not like you have the south side... or maybe better example,
brothers inherit an estate and then after a year they finally get
around to dividing the estate and one of them gets, you know,
the north side of the field and the other gets the south
side of the field. Do we say that we now say that
the north side was always the one that was going to that
brother and the south side retroactively was always going to the other?
But that was a case where it never had
been already identified and then mixed up. It existed during this grey
period where how it would be assigned later was not determined and
then do we say the way when it eventually got
assigned that
will tell us in
hindsight that was the part that was. That we might say, but
that doesn't mean that it was the initial wine, right? How could
such a thing ever work? So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* really struggles with
this, logically so, and he says the following. If you take a
look, תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* tries to re-read what יש ברירה *yesh breira*
means. And תוספות *Tosafos* says like this: ונראה *v'nira*. It is one,
two, do you see the word בו *bo*? Like five lines from
the bottom, the new תוספות *Tosafos* בו *bo*, so it is like
five lines over that, about a few words before ונראה *v'nira*. He
says, ונראה דהכא קמיבעיא ליה *v'nira d'hacha kamibay'la*. Here was really the
question. מי אמרינן לא קפיד קרא אלא אמיחה מן המגילה hamigillah שתהא
ניכרת לתוך המים שלה *mi amrinan lo kapid kra ela am'chika min
ham'gila shete'e nekeret l'toch hamayim shelo*. That the real concern is that
the focus is that the scraping be distinct for that person. אבל
לתוך כוס אחד *aval l'toch kos echad*, but now if you start
in one vessel that is not good. איכא למימר כוס שתיה shtiah
דלאו דידה *ika l'meimar kos sh'tiya d'lav dida*. So if when you
mix them up into one vessel, right, we said that would be
a problem because each person would be drinking not her water. So
תוספות *Tosafos* says the problem isn't that you just happen to be
drinking somebody else's water. That is not in itself a problem. The
problem when you're drinking it after it got mixed up into one
vessel
was לאו lav, מחיקה ניכרת היא *lav m'chika nikeres hi*. The real
problem is that if you scrape them into separate vessels and mix
them together and both women drank from the same vessel, the fact
that we're now both drinking from the same vessel sort of, you
know, conflates the two distinct processes. In the end, you don't look
at it as two distinct processes. You look at it as one
process because in the end it's all ending in one vessel that
they're both drinking from. Okay, so that is the problem. The problem
isn't just you can't drink water that wasn't yours. The problem is
that it unites the two processes. If that's the case, חזר וחילקן
הרי מים של כל אחת ניכרין *chazar v'chilkan harei mayim shel kol
achas nikarin*. So when you divide them, then everybody has their own
water. So do we say יש ברירה *yesh breira*? It doesn't mean
יש ברירה *yesh breira* like you got the water that initially was
yours. What it means is, הרי הובררו מימיה או דילמא אין ברירה
כלומר ברירת מים בשעת מחיקה בעינן אבל על תערובת דיו שכתב המגילה
hamigillah לא קפדינן שהרי בשעת מחיקה בטלה הכתב *harei huv'ru meimeha o
dilma ein breira klomar breiras mayim b'sha'as m'chika ba'inan aval al taroves
dyo shekasav ham'gila lo kapkinan sheharei b'sha'as m'chika batla haksav*. Anyway, he
goes on, it is not exactly clear but I think what he's
getting at, or it is clear but I'm reading it too fast.
But what he is getting at I believe is the following: He's
saying, you're right. You cannot say יש ברירה *yesh breira* and magically
it worked out that I'm drinking only mine. All of my water
went into my cup and all the other person's water went into
theirs. So we have to assume that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s really
saying maybe it's you don't really have to drink just your water.
You can drink somebody else's water, but the problem of being in
the same cup is that it in the end brought the two
processes together. And in the end, if even though they started as
separate, if it all ended in the same cup and each woman
is drinking from the same cup, then it really is like a
process that's not being done specifically for each woman. But if you
happen to mix them and then you divided them again, then we
could be able to say look, it was written for you, it
was scraped for you, and you're drinking your own cup. You're drinking
a cup that just you are drinking it. It might have somebody
else's water in it by accident, it got mixed up a little
bit, but it's just your cup. Maybe that is sufficient to define
it as a distinctive process for that woman and a distinctive process
for the other. Okay, but תוספות *Tosafos* says there's no way you
can say that in the end of the day if it got
mixed up and then you re-divided it that magically you got all
of your water and the other person got all of her water.
Okay, so that is the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s question. Do those things
work? And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* ends with all of that by
saying תיקו teiku. *teiku*. We don't know. The question stands. Yes. Can
you also say that
this solution has a certain efficacy depending on the individual? In other
words, that the solution when it's mixed, even though it's mixed, I'm
just thinking of another possibility. That it's like, you know, this bottle
and depending on your... Right, so that would be the idea that
you can't drink somebody else's because the solutions have different efficacies or
whatever. Is that what you're saying? No, what I'm saying is like,
here's a double portion in this bottle. But I mean it's dependent
just on the individual judgment what that's in that bottle is going
to do. Right, so really it doesn't matter. It's not like, I
mean that's a question too, which is how much are we halachic-izing
this and how much are we making this about like some magic
of the water? Right, like in this whole discussion the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* never said, well, if it was for that woman then the
water will have this power and if it's for another woman the
water will have that power. Now you're mixing them up and they
have two different powers. Like it never framed it in terms of
there being real power in the water. It only framed it like
halachically. Is it a process being done for her or is the
process also being done for the other person? Right, so I think
that's what you're saying. Like you could just say look, the water
fundamentally is neutral. It's just it all depends on the woman who's
drinking it, not on... Right. Right, I understand. It's all prepared and
has the name in it and it's twice the two amount. Right,
so I think that that is a powerful part of this, which
is like, you know, when we read this, we could be like,
whoa, you're drinking somebody else's thing. For that person it's poison and
for you it's not and you're getting the other person's poison. You
know, but the גמרא Gemara isn't looking at it in terms of,
I think, some metaphysical power of the water. It's looking at it
from a legal perspective. You know, did you do this... the process
has to be distinctive for each person and so on and so
forth. I think again that's the גמרא Gemara sort of like demystifying
it or demiracle-izing it or something. Okay. השקאה בנחושת hashka'ah bineshochet in
a way. Yeah, exactly. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
בעי רבא, Ba'ei Rava, השקה בסיב, hashka besiv,
if you made her drink with through a like a sieve, what's
it say, like something like a leaf that's wrapped around it, okay,
or
meaning that you sort of, you know, you used like used a
big
palm fiber, whatever anyway.
סיבין sivin is fiber. Okay, and you made it essentially like a
type of a funnel or something like that or a tube and
you drank through the tube, מהו? mahu? what's the הלכה? halacha? בשפופרת
מהו? bishfoperet mahu? or let's say just through a type of a
straw. Okay, what's the הלכה? halacha? תיקו. teiku, Now what's the question?
I'm sorry, I skipped a line. מדרך שתיה בכך או אין דרך
שתיה בכך? miderech shtiah bekach o ein derech shtiah bekach? Is that
a normal way of drinking? No, not תיקו, teiku. we don't know.
So תוספות says there's another גמרא Gemara that talks about eating מצה
matzah that's wrapped in up in some fibrous matter, you know, and
is that a problem or no? Like for example, it's an issue
about like swallowing pills if you have a non-כשר kosher ingredient besides
the fact that whether it's אכילה achilah or not and רפואה, refuah,
but anyway, but if it's inside of a capsule, so maybe you're
not really eating it because the capsule is surrounding it when it's
going down your throat. Actually sometimes the capsules are more problematic than
the pill because the capsules are made out of gelatin. Anyway, but
that's like the idea the גמרא Gemara talks about eating מצה, matzah,
כרכה בסיב, karchah besiv, and eating מצה matzah when it's surrounded by
a capsule, is that considered אכילה achilah or not? תוספות points out
that this case is different because this case actually the liquid is
going down your throat and is touching your throat. The the straw
is just getting it from the cup to your mouth. It's not
actually sort of serving as a חציצה, chatzitzah, as a block, as
an obstruction between the liquid and the inside of your throat. So
this question whether it's שתיה or not. So right. So yes. So
this so the point is when you're dealing with it actually surrounding
the food and it's the food is traveling down your throat surrounded
by something, that clearly is not considered אכילה. achilah. When you're dealing
with this where it's just about how to get the thing to
your word the liquid to your mouth,
that's the גמרא's Gemara question. Of course it is funny because we
think using a straw is a very natural way of drinking something,
but maybe it's still it's not the type of drinking of the
תורה. Torah. Maybe also because the תורה Torah says והשקה את המים,
vehishka et hamayim, he shall make her drink the water. Using when
you use a straw, you're using, you know, that's when you're drinking
the water. When you make somebody else drink, you don't use you
might use a funnel, I mean if you're trying to force drink
force feed somebody, but you don't you know a straw, so maybe
that's part of the question. Okay. It might be a way to
get more of the liquid and less of the dirt. What? Oh,
like oh, that's an interesting point. Maybe you're not getting the dirt
that way, and that's a problem. If you look at the side,
the side quotes the ערוך Aruch and says פירוש נתן הסיב במים
ובא הסיב למים כמין ספוג ונתן הסיב בפיה ומוצצת ומוציאה
למים. perush natan hasiv bemayim uva hasiv lamayim kemin sfog venatan hasiv
befiha umotzetzet umotzia lamayim. Okay, so you put some type of a
of a of a leaf or some type of a fiber in
the water, it absorbs the water and then you took the leaf
to your mouth and you sucked the water out of the leaf.
Okay, so you're basically doing it. So that makes more sense why
it's not דרך שתיה. derech shtiah. Because if you're just using it
as a funnel or as a straw, why is it not דרך
שתיה? derech shtiah? So that makes it a little bit more of
an interesting case. So the גמרא Gemara says תיקו. teiku, בעי רב
אשי, Ba'ei Rav Ashi, רב אשי Rav Ashi asks, נשפכו מהן ונשתיירו
מהן, nishpechu mehen venishtayru mehen, מהו? mahu? Let's say you didn't have
all the waters. Whoops, you slipped and some of it spilled out,
okay, and you're left with what remains, is that okay? תיקו, we
don't know. אמר רבי זירא אמר רב, Amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rav,
שתי שבועות האמורות בסוטה למה? shtei shevuot ha'amurot beSotah lamah? Why does
it say והשביע אותה הכהן vehishpia otah hakohen twice? Right, the פסוק
pasuk says where were we? It says the following. It says והשביע
אותה הכהן ואמר אל האשה אם לא שכב איש אותך ואם לא
שטית טומאה תחת אישך הנקי ממי המרים המאררים האלה ואת כי שטית
תחת אישך וכי נטמאת ויתן איש בך את שכבתו מבלעדי אישך. vehishpia
otah hakohen ve'amar el ha'ishah im lo shakhav ish otakh ve'im lo
satit tumah takhat ishekh hinaki mi'mei hamarim ham'arerim ha'eleh ve'at ki satit
takhat ishekh vekhi nitmet vayiten ish bakh et shikhvato mibal'adei ishekh. So
it says he makes her take this oath, if you didn't, then
you'll be cleansed, and if you did, then... and then it says
והשביע הכהן את האשה בשבועת האלה ואמר הכהן לאשה יתן ה' אותך
לאלה ולשבועה בתוך עמך בתת ה' את ירכך נפלת ואת בטנך צבה.
vehishpia hakohen et ha'ishah bishvuat ha'alah ve'amar hakohen la'ishah yiten Hashem otakh
le'alah ulishvuah betokh amekh betet Hashem et yerekh'ekh nofelet ve'et bitnekh tzahvah.
So it says again he shall make her take the oath right
before the punchline. Like he says he shall make her swear and
say if you did not do it you'll be cleansed and if
you did do it and then it doesn't have the end of
the sentence and then it again says and he shall make her
take the oath and say and then it says and here's the...
the curse: God will do such and such to you. So why
does it repeat that he shall make her take the oath the
second time? Okay, so שתי שבועות אלו למה אחת קודם שנמחקה המגילה
ואחת לאחר שנמחקה. Shtei shevuos elu lamma achas kodem she-nimchaka hamigillah v'achas
achar she-nimchaka. One before he scraped away the המגילה hamigillah and the
other after. So the גמרא Gemara says מתיב רבא תרווייהו קודם שנמחקה
מגילה כתיבן. Metiv Rava tarvaihu kodem she-nimchaka megillah kesivan. But what do
you mean? They're both in the same thing and making her take
the oath before the המגילה is scraped. You can't say that you
do one after the המגילה is scraped, that's not where it's written.
אלא אמר רבא אחת לשבועה שיש עמה אלה ואחת לשבועה שאין עמה
אלה. Ella amar Rava achas l'shevuah she-yesh imah alah v'achas l'shevuah she-ein
imah alah. One is the שבועה shvuah with the אלה alah and
the other is the שבועה shvuah without the אלה. alah. Okay now
actually that makes a lot of sense because the first והשביע v'hishbia
says if you didn't do it you'll be cleansed and if you
did do it dot dot dot it didn't end the sentence. And
then the second one says and you know God will make you
know the water will come into you for a curse. Okay, but
it doesn't still exactly explain why to divide it into two, but
he's saying there's two types of a שבועה. shvuah. A שבועה shvuah
without the אלה alah and a שבועה shvuah with the אלה. alah.
And now the גמרא Gemara is going to try to understand what
exactly is the שבועה shvuah with the אלה alah because if you
think about it the אלה alah is a curse that somebody puts
on you, the שבועה shvuah is an oath that you take to
proclaim the truth of something like you take an oath that you're
innocent or you take an oath that you're prepared for the consequences
of the water, whatever you're doing you're taking an oath about what
you are swearing to which is different than the curse. So it's
actually a problem that he says and he shall make her swear
and say to her let the water go into you for a
curse. What's she swearing about there? He's just cursing her. So that's
what he says. Yeah the second one is a שבועה shvuah with
a curse. What does that mean? So let's take a look. היכי
דמי שבועה שיש עמה אלה? Heichi dami shvuah she-yesh imah alah? What's
the שבועה shvuah with the curse? So the גמרא Gemara. says אמר
רב אבא אמר רב משביעני עליך שלא נטמאת שאם נטמאת יבואו בך.
Amar Rav Abba amar Rav mashpiani alayich she-lo nitmeis she-im nitmeis yavo'u
bach. I am making you swear, take an oath that you did
not sin, because if you sinned then the water will come into
you. So the oath that she's taking is that she did not
sin. Right. The curse that is part of the oath is: I
am letting you know that if you're lying in this oath this
is what's going to happen to you. So in a way it's
the oath that is backing up the veracity the curse is backing
up the veracity of the oath. Okay, swear truthfully and you should
know that if you're lying this is what's going to happen. So
that's the שבועה שיש עמה אלה shvuah she-yesh imah alah and that
was the second והשביע v'hishbia because there was the curse was part
of that or was the only thing mentioned in the פסוקים. pesukim.
היכי דמי שבועה? Heichi dami shvuah? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
so שאם נטמאת יבואו בך. she-im nitmeis yavo'u bach. אמר רבא אלה
לחוד קיימא ושבועה לחוד קיימא. Amar Rava alah l'chud kaima u'shvuah l'chud
kaima. That's a שבועה shvuah and an אלה, alah, but it's not
the שבועה shvuah doesn't have the אלה alah as part of it.
It's you take your oath and then I say if you're lying
you're going to be cursed. Okay, but the curse is not part
of the oath. אלא אמר רבא משביעני עליך שאם נטמאת יבואו בך.
Ella amar Rava mashpiani alayich she-im nitmeis yavo'u bach. I am having
you swear and say I am saying if you have sinned these
waters will enter into you. Okay,
so that's a curse, where's the oath? So the way רש"י Rashi
says it is you're actually משביע mashpia the oath, you're not משביע
mashpia the woman. You're basically sort as it were saying to the
oath: you oath, I am משביע mashpia you that you have to
do your job and that you have to go into the woman
and you know curse her that you know if she sinned. So
let's take a look. אמר רב אשי אלה איכא שבועה ליכא. Amar
Rav Ashi alah ika shvuah leka. You're not making her take a
שבועה, shvuah, you're just in a way saying I am swearing that
the water will enter into that the curse will take effect on
you. But what is she saying that is right what is she
swearing to that has in it the curse that's going to take
effect to her? אלא אמר רב אשי משביעני עליך שלא נטמאת שאם
נטמאת יבואו בך. Ella amar Rav Ashi mashpiani alayich she-lo nitmeis she-im
nitmeis yavo'u bach. I am making you swear that you did not
sin and if you sinned let the water come into you. Now
it's not exactly clear how's that different than what we said before?
If you look before the first line was משביעני עליך שלא נטמאת
שאם נטמאת יבואו בך. Mashpiani alayich she-lo nitmeis she-im nitmeis yavo'u bach.
So the first one was: swear you didn't sin because if you
did this is what will happen. And this was one: משביעני עליך
שלא נטמאת ואם נטמאת יבואו בך. Mashpiani alayich she-lo nitmeis v'im nitmeis
yavo'u bach. So that's not just saying and so this by the
way is what will happen if you did sin, it's two things.
Number one: swear you didn't sin. Number two: if you did sin
you'll be cursed. Still like, how is the oath part of the
curse? How is it any different? So it's a little confusing or
more than a little. You look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says
משביעני עליך שלא נטמאת ואם נטמאת יבואו בך, Mashpiani alayich she-lo nitmeis
v'im nitmeis yavo'u bach, that's different than שאם נטמאת יבואו בך. she-im
nitmeis yavo'u bach. רש"י Rashi says משביעני עליך שיהא אמת מה שאמרת
לפנינו שלא נטמאת. Mashpiani alayich she-yehai emes mah she-amart lefaneinu she-lo nitmeis.
So first you take your oath that you're telling... telling the truth,
that's the שבועה shevuah *shvuah*. You, the woman, are swearing that you're
telling the truth. ואם נטמאת *ve'im nitmet*, not just by the way
parenthetically, like we said before, if you're lying you'll be cursed, then
all you have really is the oath because the the curse is
parenthetical. So no, you have the oath and number one, take the
oath. Number two, ואם נטמאת יבואו בך מים לקיים שבועת האשה שלא
נטמאת ואלה שתחול *ve'im nitmet yavo'u bach mayim lekayem shvuat ha-ishah shelo
nitmet ve-alah shetachul*. So Rashi's saying there's no way the woman takes
an oath about the אלה Alah. *alah*. The oath is only a
woman attesting to the own veracity of her statement. So basically there
are really two oaths going on here. Number one is the oath
that the woman takes: I am swearing that I'm telling the truth.
And the other is the oath that the כהן *Kohen* is making
as it were, sort of like calling upon the curse to take
effect on the woman. Like you know sort of the same way
like Moshe says, you know, האזינו השמים ואעידה בכם היום את השמים
ואת הארץ *Ha'azinu hashamayim ve'ahida bacham hayom et hashamayim ve'et ha'aretz*. Like
I call on heaven and earth to be witnesses. So I'm calling
on the curse. I am forswearing the curse like they used to
forswear angels, you know, to make sure the angels would do their
bidding. I forswear the curse that the curse should fill out its
duty and take effect on the woman. So the כהן *Kohen* is
being משביע *mashbia* the curse to do its duty and משביע *mashbia*
the woman that she's telling the truth, but you never actually have
a שבועה *shvuah* that itself relate by the woman that itself relates
to the curse. Because the שבועה *shvuah* of the woman is only
a testimony that she is telling the truth, so there's no way
that the שבועה *shvuah* could be you could have her agree to
I accept the punishment that will come on me if I'm lying,
but that's still not a שבועה *shvuah* like the שבועה *shvuah* shall
just be about attesting to the veracity of her statement. So it's
a complicated like what exactly this tightrope is the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is walking about שבועה שיש עמה אלה *shvuah she-yesh imah alah*. At
the end of the day, it really seems like the way it's
defining its terms that there's a שבועה *shvuah* and an אלה *alah*,
not some combination
of the two, but somehow they're being wrapped together. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. The idea that you can't test against
yourself.
So therefore she can't maybe like you can't be משים עצמו רשע
*mesim atzmo rasha* so you have to make the oath what's going
yeah maybe. Okay, let's take a look at the משנה Mishnah. *Mishna*.
אמן אמן Amen, Amen *amen amen*, what is she saying אמן אמן
Amen, Amen. *amen amen* about? אמרה האשה אמן אמן amen amen *amra
ha-ishah amen amen*, what's the double אמן Amen *amen*? So אמן Amen
על האלה אמן Amen על השבועה *amen al ha-alah amen al ha-shvuah*.
So we're back now to the אלה *alah* and the שבועה *shvuah*.
Okay, so אמן Amen *amen* yes because you said you know I'm
making you swear that you're telling the truth, אמן Amen *amen* means
yes, I am swearing that I'm telling the truth. And here אמן
amen *amen* on the אלה *alah*, forget the previous גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
which I have always found very confusing, but the אמן Amen, *amen*
on the אלה *alah* is what we were saying before: let this
water come in and curse you if you're lying. אמן *amen*, yes,
I accept forget the שבועה *shvuah*. Yes, I accept it. A, I
assert that I'm telling the truth, that's the שבועה *shvuah*, אמן *amen*.
And yes, אמן *amen*, I accept the punishment if I'm lying, the
שבועה *shvuah* and the אלה *alah*, fine. אמן מאיש זה אמן מאיש
אחר Amen me'ish zeh, Amen me'ish acher. *amen me-ish zeh amen me-ish
acher*. Yes, I accept the punishment and I assert my truthfulness that
I did not commit adultery whether this man or even a man
I wasn't directly suspected about with my husband, but I'm denying any
adultery ever
against my husband. And we learn from this by the way, this
is a principle we learn in other places, the same way סוטה
Sotah *Sotah* becomes a principle to learn by טומאה *tumah*, ספק טומאה
ברשות הרבים *safek tumah birshut harabim*, ספק טומאה ברשות היחיד *safek tumah
birshut hayachid*, another important basis for other areas of הלכה halakhah *Halakha*
סוטה Sotah? *Sotah* is, is the issue called גלגול שבועה *gilgul shvuah*.
That once you have an ability to get a guy up on
the stand and make him take one oath, because you know you
need a certain concrete basis to allow you to force a guy
to take an oath in court, once you've been able to force
him to take one oath, you can throw in anything you want
to make him swear about. What you have to imagine then, like
it's a real disadvantage to ever have to be you know to
ever get in a position where you have to swear about anything,
right? So
anyway, that's called גלגול שבועה *gilgul shvuah*, like to roll from one
שבועה *shvuah* to the next. So since the husband is entitled to
make her take the oath about the man she's suspected about, actually
she actually is being also forced to take an oath and to
swear that she did not commit adultery with any man, yes. So
we're saying she's answering אמן *amen* to her own affirmation? No, the
כהן *Kohen* says אמן אמן amen amen *amen amen*. One אמן *amen*
is to her own affirmation, declaration? No, meaning one
to the אלה *alah*
and one to the שבועה *shvuah*. No, but that was the first
point, but the second point is just I mean the second point,
I wouldn't interpret it as like I'm saying אמן *amen* to what
I just said. It's like when you say I make you swear
you didn't do this, yes, yes, yes, yes, I didn't do that.
It's sort of like an in saying like I didn't do that
or anything like it. Sort of like the doubling is a way
of sort of saying that and anything like connected to that I'm
asserting that I did not do, okay? Of course, though, it makes
you remember that famous line by there's this guy, what's his name,
Morgan, that you know what I'm going to
say. Anyway, he's like this philosopher but he always had these one
line zingers so he was at a lecture once and somebody was
up there and saying and saying yeah whatever and somebody was up
there and saying, you know, it's very strange that like a double
negative is a positive but a double positive isn't a negative. So
he's in the audience and he says yeah, yeah.
Anyway,
so that's אמן אמן. I don't think that's the אמן אמן here,
okay? That's a different yeah, yeah. That's a yes, yes, yes. Okay.
אמן אמן. אמן מאיש זה אמן מאיש אחר. Amen me-ish zeh amen
me-ish acher. אמן שלא שטיתי ארוסה ונשואה. Amen shelo satisi arusah unesua.
Now, the husband could only do this to her basically when she's
a נשואה. nesua. Okay, but now that he's making her swear it
would have been adultery had she slept with another man even when
she was an ארוסה. arusah. So now that he's making her swear,
that אמן can also include whether she had committed adultery not only
with a different man than she's suspected of but even from an
earlier period in their marriage when she was just an ארוסה. arusah.
And number one, ושומרת יבמה מכונסה. veshomeret yevama mekunesah. Let's say she's
married to her husband not through קידושין Kiddushin but through יבום. Yibbum.
So and so once he's done יבום Yibbum they're full husband and
wife. So he can make her go through the סוטה Sotah process
if he suspects her of committing adultery. Now, once she's doing that
he can make the אמן can also will also refer to that
she did not commit adultery when she was awaiting the יבום Yibbum
after her husband died when she was awaiting יבום. Yibbum. So the
גמרא Gemara is going to ask on that because until this point
all these acts of adultery would have made her whether a different
man, whether קידושין, Kiddushin, would have made her forbidden to her husband.
But it's not at all פשוט pashut that when a woman is
awaiting יבמה yevama that if she sleeps with another man she's not
really an אשת איש. Eshesh Ish. It's only an איסור לאו issur
lav לא תהיה אשת המת החוצה לאיש זר. lo tihiyeh eshes hamess
hachutzah le'ish zar. It's not clear that if she sleeps with another
man that somehow makes her forbidden to the brother-in-law, okay? So that
wouldn't be would that be considered an act of adultery? So the
גמרא Gemara is going to
ask about that. אמן שלא נטמאתי, Amen shelo nitmesi, אמן that I
did not commit adultery, ואם נטמאתי יבואו בי, ve'im nitmesi yavo'u vi,
okay? And if I did, then let them come into me. So
that sounds to me like the אמן to the שבועה אמן to
the אלה. Not exactly clear to me, and that's basically what רש״י
Rashi says. אמן שלא נטמאתי Amen shelo nitmesi היינו קבלת שבועה haynu
kabbalas shevuah ואם נטמאתי יבואו בי ve'im nitmesi yavo'u vi היינו קבלת
אלה. haynu kabbalas Alah. I swear I'm telling the truth and I
accept the consequences if I am not. רבי מאיר אומר, אמן שלא
נטמאתי Rebbe Meir omer Amen shelo nitmeisi. אמן שלא אטמא. Amen shelo
etama. So yes I did not do it and B, I won't
commit adultery in the future. So that's for like that's not an
oath about what happened, that's a promise about the future. And that
says so anyway the גמרא Gemara, is going to say it's not
to say that if in the future she commits it's not to
say that she will right now be punished by the water because
God's going to look into the future and determine that what she's
planning, sort of like that Minority Report, you know? But of course
if she blows up now then she never will have done it
in the future, so how would that work? No, but what it
means is is that if she does it in the future, when
she commits adultery the water will then have the effect at that
time. The oath will then... that's the way it's being... it carries
on. Can they never bring her up for סוטה? Sotah Ah, excellent,
so we're going to get to that. Yes, she there's no double
jeopardy. Oh, very good point. Okay. אמן שלא אטמא. הכל שווים שאין
מתנה עמה על קודם שתתארס. Kol shavin she'ein masnin imah al kodem
shetisares. Everybody agrees, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir adds the future, but everybody
agrees that you cannot make her swear about something about before קידושין
Kiddushin because then whether she's slept around or not or whether she
was married to another guy before she was married to this guy,
it's none of this guy's business. Okay? So he can't make her
take an oath about anything she did before קידושין. Kiddushin. ולא על
אחר שתתגרש Velo al achar shetisgaresh and he can't make her take
an oath, and even according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that thinks
it can be future-oriented, it would not relate to time after they
got divorced. If they were to ever get divorced and she was
to sleep with another man, let's say she even married a second
husband and committed adultery with you know against the second husband, it's
none of the first husband's business. So his oath cannot even if
it can apply to the past and according to רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir the future, it's only during the period of their marriage, not
before their marriage and not after their marriage. Okay. ולא אחר שתתגרש.
Velo achar shetisgaresh. נסתרה לאחד ונטמאת ואחר כך החזירה לא היה מתנה
עמה. Nisterah leachad venitmes ve'achar kach hichzirah lo haya masne imah.
Now, what happens if... so there's a little confusing the text here.
The ב״ח Bach has all this discussion of the text. But basically
what it means is
he cannot make her take an oath to relate to a circumstance
even if he says I want you to swear that you'll never
commit adultery even after we get divorced in the eventuality that I'll
remarry you after the divorce. Like, too bad. It's like when she'd
be sleeping with that other man it would be after the divorce
and before the remarry, so it's really none of his business. Okay?
She can get married to the same husband under those circumstances? Yes,
if she didn't marry... if she didn't... marry a second guy in
between, even if she slept with a second guy she can go
back to her first husband. Okay. Right. Yes. It's only if she
married a second guy in between. Although the תורה Torah says אחרי
אשר הטמאה, acharei asher huttamaa, but whatever. Yeah. So but you can't.
Now רש"י Rashi another way of reading this is if he divorced
her and remarried her, he cannot make her take an oath that
she'd not let's say he did divorce her and remarried her and
now we're in the time that they have been remarried and he's
now suspects her again, he cannot make her take an oath about
the period of her about her behavior during the period of
divorce. Right. Okay. Okay. והמשנה, ve-ha-mishnah, זה כלל, zeh klal, כל שבביאה,
kol she-bi-ybeah, לא היתה אסורה לו, lo hayetah asurah lo, any circumstance
where were she'd have had sex it would not make her forbidden
to him, לא היה מתנה עמה, lo hayah matneh immah, he does
not have any ability to make her take an oath about her
behavior or to you know about the effect of the water. I
do want to say something that's not clear from this משנה. Mishnah,
In the end we talk about what to be מתנה עמה, matneh
immah, what could he stipulate, what could he extend the oath to.
So when we say in the beginning that אמן אמן goes on
when I was an ארוסה, arusah, when I was a שומרת יבם,
shomeret yavam, מאיש זה, me-ish zeh, מאיש אחר, me-ish acher, is that
implicit or does he have to say that explicitly? Is he entitled
to say "I want you to also swear it was with no
other man, I want you to also swear from before the נשואין"?
nissuin Or is that implicit? Because by the end, we're talking about
that he's not allowed to extend it to periods when she was
not married to him. We're but it sounds like before, it wasn't
just implicit, it sounds like he was act he was choosing to
extend it to those times. So that's not clear from the משנה,
Mishnah whether we think that this other range of אמן אמן that
it could extend to, is that automatic or does he have to
explicitly extend it to include those other cases? The word מתנה matneh
does not mean clearly it must be before? It does, but he
uses מתנה matneh for the things he's not able to do. When
it says what it does extend to: אמן שלא שטיתי ארוסה ולא
שטיתי ארוסה ולא שטיתי נשואה, Amen she-lo satisi arusah ve-lo satisi arusah
ve-lo satisi nesuah, אמן מאיש זה אמן מאיש אחר. It doesn't say
that he was מתנה עמה, matneh immah, it just says that's what
she's saying אמן to. So you know, so that's my question. Okay
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara אמר רב המנונא, Amar
Rav Hamnuna, שומרת יבם שזינתה, shomeret yavam she-zintah, אסורה ליבמה. asurah li-yvama.
If the woman awaiting יבום yibbum sleeps with another man, she is
now forbidden to do יבום yibbum with the brother. Why? ממאי? mimmai?
How do you know? מדקתני, mi-dikhtani, שומרת יבם וכנוסה, shomeret yavam ve-khnusah,
that he can make her swear about her behavior when she was
a שומרת יבם. shomeret yavam. אי אמרת בשלמא, iy amrat bishlama, אסורה,
asurah, if were she to have slept with another man when she
was a when she was awaiting יבום, yibbum, so she would be
forbidden to the brother, so משום הכי מתנה בהדה, mishum hakhi matneh
ba-hada,
then he can make her swear about that, then he can stipulate
about that. Notice again the word מתנה, matneh, he can stipulate. We're
not talking about what's automatic, it sounds like he has to choose
to stipulate that. Okay. But anyway we understand how it could extend
to that, because that would have been an act that would have
made her forbidden. So that shows that doing that makes her forbidden.
אלא אי אמרת, Ella iy amrat, לא אסירה, lo asira, but if
sleeping with a man when she's שומרת יבם shomeret yavam does not
make her forbidden, היכי מתנה בהדה? heikhi matneh ba-hada? How can he
stipulate that the water and the oath extend to that to that
behavior? אלא התנן, Ella ha-tnan, the end of the משנה Mishnah says,
זה כלל כל שאילו תיבעל לא תיאסר לו, zeh klal kol she-ilu
tiba'el lo te'aser lo, לא היה מתנה עמה. lo hayah matneh immah.
Any any situation in which if she had sex it would not
make her forbidden, he cannot stipulate. So it's very im it's quite
implicit in the משנה Mishnah that if she sleeps with another man
while she's שומרת יבם, shomeret yavam, she's not able to undergo יבום,
yibbum, that that makes her forbidden to the brother-in-law. Okay.
So let's take a look. So אמרי במערבא, amrei bi-ma'arava, they said
in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, לית הלכתא כרב המנונא. leis hilkheta ke-rav
hamnuna. That seems like a pretty darn good argument. Nevertheless, we don't
rule that way. Why? אלא הא דקתני, Ella ha-dikhtani, שומרת יבם וכנוסה,
shomeret yavam ve-khnusah, how about the fact that the משנה Mishnah. is
pretty clear that if a woman as a שומרת יבם shomeret yavam
sleeps with a man she's forbidden? So how could we not rule
that way? We don't rule that way not because we don't think
it's פשט pshat in the משנה. Mishnah. He's right, that is פשט
pshat in the משנה. Mishnah It's just that's a sing that's just
a דעת יחיד. da'as yachid. הא מני רבי עקיבא היא. Ha-manni Rabbi
Akiva hi. That's the opinion of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. דאמר אין
קידושין תופסין בחייבי לאוין, de-amar ein kiddushin topsin be-khayavei lavin, ומשוי לה
כערוה. u-meshavei leh ke-ervah.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva holds in general, not just by שומרת יבם,
shomeret yavam, קידושין kiddushin is not binding by an איסור לאו. issur
lav. Take for example, let's talk about a simp case of an
איסור לאו, issur lav, I don't know, a ממזר. mamzer. Okay. I
mean there's also let's say a כהן וגרושה kohen ve-grushah but that's
not an איסור, issur, that's שוה בכל. shaveh ba-kol. So we'll take
an easier איסור לאו, issur lav, a ממזר. mamzer. Okay. Or לא
יבא עמוני ומואבי בקהל ה', lo yavo ammoni u-moavi bi-kehal hashem, so
you have an עמוני גר. ammoni ger. Okay. And you try to
do קידושין. kiddushin. Is it binding? So the basis of הלכה halakhah
is, yeah, it's binding, you're over on an איסור issur but it's
binding. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says no, it's not binding, it's anything
that's prohibited even בדיעבד bidi'avad the קידושין kiddushin won't be binding. Now
let's say, right, now let's say what by now let's ask another
question. What type of sexual act creates a ממזר? mamzer? So the
basis of הלכה is when an איסור כרת issur karet Is violated.
Okay, so for a guy sleeps with his sister or with a
married woman, those are the two most obvious. Interestingly נידה's nida an
exception to that. Okay, but with עריות arayos or an אשת איש,
eishes ish, that's an איסור כרת, isur kares, ממזר's mamzer created. What
about if, I don't know, a guy sleeps with a, well, if
a ממזר, mamzer, ממזר mamzer is created, but that's for a different
reason. A guy sleeps with an עמוני גר, Amoni Ger, okay?
So or that doesn't create a ממזר, mamzer, that's an איסור לאו,
isur lav, that's not an איסור כרת. isur kares. So רבי עקיבא
Rebbi Akiva says no, same way that there's no קידושין kiddushin with
this other person, like it's the same logic. If קידושין kiddushin isn't
possible, then the relationship is fundamentally excluded. Right? It's not just prohibited,
it's fundamentally ex- you know, like not unable to be a defined
relationship that has any effect. Therefore the product of that is also
a ממזר. mamzer. So רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says that there's no
קידושין kiddushin with חייבי לאוין chayvei lavin and the child is a
ממזר. mamzer. That's sort of... Now it's a question whether that is
exactly what רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva said and how the גמרא explains
what רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva initially said, but that's the basic approach.
So what the גמרא is saying is the following: what's the logic
to say that the woman is forbidden by case of שומרת יבם?
shomeres yabam? Normally the only time a woman is forbidden under husband
is when she commits adultery, right? Which is the איסור אשת איש.
isur eishes ish. Can you get that? Okay, I'll explain it to
you again. So normally a woman is only forbidden to her husband
when she... okay, normally a woman's only forbidden to her husband when
she commits adultery, right? Which is the איסור אשת איש, isur eishes
ish, which it's not true by the case of יבום. yibum. So
but the גמרא thinks well maybe though, and you could ask a
similar question, is קידושין תופסין kiddushin tofsan by a שומרת יבם? shomeres
yabam? Is there a ממזר mamzer by a שומרת יבם? shomeres yabam?
Why? It's a simple לאו, lav, so normally, forgetting רבי עקיבא, Rebbi
Akiva, normally we should say קידושין kiddushin would be binding, you would
not have a ממזר. mamzer. But maybe since conceptually it's a continuation
of the dead brother's marriage and it's seen as resting in potential
and waiting to be actualized. So even though it's only a לאו,
lav. it's not an איסור מיתה isur misa etc. etc. But it's
a quasi-marriage already to the second brother, so maybe that's enough to
say that קידושין kiddushin won't be binding to another man, the child
will be a ממזר mamzer and so on. That seems to have
been רב המנונא's Rav Hamnuna point. He wasn't talking about רבי עקיבא.
Rebbi Akiva. He was talking about what's special about יבום. yibum. Because
יבום yibum was a quasi-marriage,
that's why if this woman sleeps with another man, it's considered like
adultery. And that's why she can no longer do יבום yibum with
the brother-in-law because it's a quasi-marriage. It's a זיקה. zika. Yes, זיקה.
zika. And then the גמרא comes back and says no, it's not
special about יבום. yibum. It's not something that would be our general
approach. We do not look at יבום yibum this way and it's
not a special status of יבום. yibum. This is just part of
a general position of רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva that would say this
by any woman who's forbidden by a לאו. So it's not because
יבום yibum is a quasi-marriage that it's a type of a quasi-adultery
that makes her forbidden, that would make the child a ממזר, mamzer,
that would make קידושין kiddushin not binding etc. This really would be
just because of the special weight that רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva gives
to any איסור לאו. isur lav. And therefore, now of course it's
a little different because this is the only איסור לאו isur lav
that relates to a binding between a man and a woman. Meaning
if a woman is a מצרי גר Mitzri ger or whatever, you
know, or he's an עמוני גר Amoni ger or whatever it might
be. So I mean, but what does it mean? It means that
they can't get married, but it doesn't mean if the woman sleeps
with another man because there's no relationship to impact. The only time
there's a relationship to impact through an act of sex is either
marriage or שומרת יבם. shomeres yabam. Otherwise there's never any defined relationship.
So there's never any other example of an איסור לאו isur lav
that makes a woman forbidden to a man, okay, through that act,
there not to be a type of a cheating on the guy
which only exists through marriage or שומרת יבם. shomeres yabam. But nevertheless
what the גמרא is saying is this is not a special status
of יבם yabam that everybody would agree to. You know, yes you
wanted to say because it's a quasi-marriage, actually that's not true. If
you put רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva aside, if a שומרת יבם shomeres
yabam sleeps with another man she's not forbidden to the brother-in-law and
the child isn't a ממזר. mamzer. And if she accepts קידושין kiddushin
from another man it will be a binding קידושין. kiddushin. This is
just רבי עקיבא's Rebbi Akiva position that generally treats איסורי לאוין issurei
lavin very weightily, so according to him that's why she's forbidden to
her husband. Now you had a question before? I just don't, I
mean wouldn't that align with the fact we should yell at רבי
עקיבא Rebbi Akiva and right that he's creating too many ממזרים? mamzerim?
Yeah, we don't go by that, right? Like we don't פסקן pasken
like רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, which is what the ירושלמי Yerushalmi said.
You're right in interpreting the משנה Mishnah that the woman, the משנה
Mishna. assumes that a שומרת יבם shomeres yabam who sleeps with another
man is forbidden to her husband, but you're wrong in assuming that
that's a unanimous opinion and we פסקן pasken that way. It's all
part of a רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva package who gives extra weight
to איסורי לאוין. issurei lavin. Yeah. Would רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva apply
that statement to a married man who has sex with a פנויה,
penuyah, with another פנויה, penuyah, with another woman?
Well, that assumes that that's an איסור לאו. isur lav. Which is
a very big debate. But, okay, so let's take a look. Okay.
So the גמרא says like this. אמר שטייקא בעי רבי ירמיה. Amar
shteika baei Rebbe Yirmiyah. רבי ירמיה Rebbe Yirmiyah asks, מהו שיתנה אדם
על נישואין הראשונים על נישואי אחיו? Mahu sheyatneh adam al nisuin harishonim
al nisuei achiv? Or על נישואין ראשונים al nisuin rishonim or על
נישואי אחיו al nisuei achiv מהו? mahu?
So what's the story? Meaning basically a guy married a woman and
then divorced her and then remarried her. Can he now in the
second marriage, and now in the second marriage he's suspecting her of
adultery and he's making her undergo the סוטה Sotah process?
During this סוטה process of the second marriage can he say, I
want you to swear that you never cheated on me during the
first marriage? Okay. By the way, again notice the word מתנה. matneh.
It seems like if he wants to extend it, he has to
explicitly stipulate. Okay. Or let's say he did יבום. yibum. Can now
after he's done יבום, yibum, fine, he can't say I want you
to swear that you never committed adultery, that you never slept with
a man while you were שומרת יבם, shomeret yavam, because we don't
פסקן pasken that that's רבי עקיבא. Rebbe Akiva. Can he say, I
want you to swear to me that you never cheated on my
dead brother? Okay. Because if you see this marriage as an extension
of the marriage with the brother, so that's like taking it one
step up. A, can he make her swear that you never cheated
on me in one case during our first marriage, which isn't the
marriage right now? And B, how about if that first marriage actually
wasn't with me, but was with my brother? Can you make her
swear about that? Because this is seen as a continuation of, so
that would be different than them being able to swear to a
future marriage. We already said. Right.
Well, well, no, רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir says you can make her
swear for future marriage. I mean, even for the future, it's for
the future of this marriage, not for the future of getting divorced
and remarried. So you're saying... you can't the future, yeah, but maybe
past is better than future. I mean, you know, okay, let's take
a look. נישואי אחיו, nisuei achiv, in other words this present husband
is the יבם. yavam. Yeah. That's but that's a second taste, the
first, okay. תא שמע, Ta shema, וזה הכלל, v'zeh haklal, כל שתיבעל
ולא תיאסר לו, kol shetiba'el velo te'aser lo, לא היה מתנה עמה.
lo hayah matneh immah.
Anytime were she to have sex, she would not be forbidden to
him, then he cannot make her swear. הא אסירה, Ha asira, but
in these cases, were she to have committed sex, were she to
have had sex with another man during their first marriage, or were
she to have cheated on his dead brother during the brother's marriage,
then she would be forbidden to him. Right? If this woman had
committed adultery during their first marriage, they could not be allowed to
be remaining married right now, right? She because... or if she had
committed adultery with the brother, I'm sorry, when she was married to
the brother, then you can't, you don't do
יבום. yibum. If a woman is a סוטה and the husband dies,
the brother doesn't do יבום. yibum. If she commits adultery with the
man, then there's no יבום yibum with this woman. So in those
cases, דוקא davka because it is the past, which would mean that
she would be forbidden now had that happened, that is acceptable. So
Jenny, you're absolutely right. Of course, רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir, you cannot
make her say, I make you swear that if we get divorced
and remarried, that you won't have, you know, that you won't cheat
on me. You know, that you can't say, because, but you can
say about a previous marriage that we've had together, because in that
case she'd be forbidden to me right now, so I can make
you swear about that. Okay. הכי נמי דמתנה שמע מינה. Hachi nami
dematneh shema mina. That's a good proof. Let's go on. רבי מאיר
אומר Rabbi Meir omer, אמן שלא נטמאתי. You can even talk about
not, about an oath about what will be the future. But again,
that will take effect during the future.
תני תנא ברייתא, Tani tana braitah, לא כשאמר רבי מאיר אמן שלא
אטמא. lo kshe'amar Rebbe Meir Amen shelo etma. I swear that I
won't become טמאה. tmeiah. שאם תטמא מים בודקין אותה מעכשיו, she'im titma
mayim bodkin osah me'achshav, that then now, if she's gonna do it
in the future, now the water will take an effect, like I
said, punishing her for the future, which something hasn't happened yet. אלא
לכשתטמא, ella l'cheshtitma, when, if, if he says, swear to me about
the future and she says אמן, then when she, if and when
she were to commit adultery in the future, מים מערערין אותה ובודקין
אותה. mayim me'ar'arin osah uvodekin osah. Then the water like, you know,
regurgitated itself in her, stirred itself up in her, and then it
would have its impact. Okay. בעי רב
אשי, Baei Rav Ashi, מהו שיתנה אדם על נישואין האחרונים? mahu sheyatneh
adam al nisuin ha'achronim?
השתא? Hashta? התם מי לא אסטירא ליה, Hatam mi lo astira leh,
או דילמא זימנין דמגרשה והדר מהדר לה. o dilma zimnin demagrashah vehadar
mehadar lah. So can a man make her swear on the second,
on the remarriage? So this sort of seems to be
what was sort of being referred to explicitly in the גמרא, I
mean in the משנה. Mishna
But, hold on, let me just double-check רש"י, Rashi, make sure I'm
explaining this correctly.
Yeah.
Yeah. So the first thing is that according to one גרסה, girsa,
that could have been what actually the גמרא was saying. על אחת
שתתגרש ותיסתרה. Al achas shetisgaresh vesissaterah.
But anyway, this is the question he's asking. According to רבי מאיר
Rebbe Meir that she can swear about the future, can you make
her swear that if we get divorced and remarried, you won't cheat
on me then? Okay. So, oh no, no, no, I'm sorry. The
משנה Mishna. says that you can't make her swear that if we
get remarried you won't have cheated on me in the interim. Right.
That was the משנה. That you can't make her swear that she
wouldn't have cheated during the interim. So now we're
saying... Because
then she would be forbidden right now. So according to רבי מאיר
*Rabbi Meir* that it can also be future oriented, can you say,
I want you to swear that you won't cheat on me later
in our marriage or if we ever get divorced and remarry you
won't cheat on me then either? Can that also work? Okay? because
if she were to do that, he would be forbidden to him
at that time. Okay, so let's take a look. השתא מיהא לא
אסירה ליה *Hashta meiha lo asira lei*, now if I mean he
wouldn't be forbidden in the context of this marriage. So maybe, you
know, if she were to cheat on him in a remarriage situation,
it wouldn't be forbidden in the context of this marriage, so maybe
he can't make her swear. או דילמא זימנין מגרש לה ומהדר לה
*O dilma zimnin megaresh lah u'mehader lah*, no, because sometimes he'll divorce
and remarry, and if she were to do it then, she would
be forbidden to him in the context of the second marriage. So
maybe she can make him, he can make her swear right now
that she won't do that, she won't cheat on him even in
a second marriage. תא שמע *Ta shma*, come and hear. הכל שוים
שלא יתנה עמה *Hakol shavin she'lo yatne imah*, everybody would agree that
he cannot make her, that he could not swear like stipulate about
her, you know, regarding, לא קודם שתתארס *lo kodem she'titares*, the time
before the marriage, ולא אחר שתתגרש *ve'lo acher she'titgaresh*, and not after
she gets divorced. נסתרה לאחד ונטמאת אחר יחזירנה לא יתנה *Nistera le'echad
ve'nitmet acher yachzirana lo yatne*. So and he can't make her swear
that if she wasn't private with a man, that she basically did
not sleep with a man during the period before the remarry, okay,
so that's what the משנה *Mishna* says. He can't make her swear
that she didn't sleep with a guy in the or that she
won't or that she won't sleep with a guy during the interim
period. הא יחזירנה ותטמא *Ha yachzirana ve'titma*,
but regarding whether sleeping with a guy after the remarriage, הכא נמי
דמתני *hacha nami damatne*, the משנה *Mishna* does not say he can't
do that, presumably he can do that. שמע מינה *Shma mina*. So
basically it works very nicely in parallel. He can make her swear
that she didn't cheat on him during a first marriage, if this
is a second, if he was married to her in the first
marriage, not with a different guy. And he can also make her
swear according to רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* that it's future oriented, that
she won't cheat on him during a second marriage to him, if
they were to get divorced and remarry. Okay, תנו רבנן *Tanu rabanan*,
now we get to the double jeopardy. זאת תורת הקנאת *Zot Torat
HaKnaot*, this is the law of jealousy. מלמד שאשה שותה ושונה *Melamed
she'isha shota ve'shona*, so תורה *Torah* is an expansive word. So she
can actually be made to drink twice. She can be suspected twice.
רבי יהודה אומר *Rabbi Yehuda omer*, זאת *zot*, no, this, which is
a limiting word, שאינה שותה ושונה *she'eina shota ve'shona*, no double jeopardy,
she can't be made to drink twice. אמר רבי יהודה *Amar Rabbi
Yehuda*, מעשה והעיד לפנינו נחוניא חופר שיחין *maaseh ve'heid lefanenu Nechunya Chofer
Shichin*, so נחוניא *Nechunya* the digger of wells testified to us שהאשה
שותה ושונה *she'ha'isha shota ve'shona*, that he actually testified, which sounds like
is he testifying about a tradition or is he testifying about having
witnessed something? תוספות *Tosafot* actually quote a ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*, if you look
at תוספות *Tosafot*, אינה שותה ושונה *eina shota ve'shona*, ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*, קורקמית
תוכיח ששתתה ושנתה ושלשה *Korkemit tochach she'shatta ve'shanta ve'shilsha* לפני שמעיה ואבטליון
*lifnei Shemaya ve'Avtalyon*. Okay,
so actually testifying that it actually occurred. Somebody wrote a book called
הטקס שלא היה *Hatekes shelo haya*, The Ritual That Never Happened, about
סוטה *Sota*. So actually according to the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*, it actually did
happen. And there was one woman who they did, who it was
done three times with her in front of שמעיה ואבטליון *Shemaya ve'Avtalyon*.
Must be she was innocent at least the first two times. Okay,
so anyway, okay, so the question is, so when he says that
this person testified, did he testify to a tradition of a הלכה
*halacha* or did he testify to actually having witnessed it? But anyway,
so נחוניא חופר שיחין *Nechunya Chofer Shichin* testified שהאשה שותה ושונה *she'ha'isha
shota ve'shona*,
that she can be made to do it twice. וקבלנו עדותו *Vekibalnu
eduto*, now, we only were prepared to accept that הלכה *halacha* position,
not in all cases, but בשני אנשים *bishnei anashim*, if it was
two different husbands, אבל לא באיש אחד *aval lo be'ish echad*, not
the same husband. Okay, so with the same husband, no double jeopardy.
He made her go through it once, he can't make her go
through it again. But with another husband, maybe yes. So if that's
true, when the תנא קמא *Tana Kama* says you can go through
it twice, presumably the תנא קמא *Tana Kama* means even the same
husband, okay? So you have רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* saying twice with
different husbands, but not the same husband. And the תנא קמא *Tana
Kama* presumably saying twice even with the same husband. And now we're
just going to have the third opinion, and then we'll unpack this
tomorrow on שבת *Shabbat*. וחכמים אומרים אין אשה שותה ושונה בין באיש
אחד בין בשני אנשים *Vechachamim omrim ein isha shota veshona bein be'ish
echad bein bishnei anashim*. Nope. No double jeopardy whether the same husband
or different husbands. Okay, so the whole range of opinions. Either you
can always be made to go twice, even the same husband, he
suspects her again a week later, you can be back here a
week later. That's the תנא קמא *Tana Kama*. רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*
says no, same guy once she's already been proven innocent, we don't
want to. From this husband again. He's just got a suspicious nature
and we don't want to hear it from the same husband. A
different husband, maybe. And then the third opinion is, no, she's totally
free from ever having to come back to court again, even with
a different husband, once she was forced to undergo this ordeal, we're
never going to make her undergo this ordeal again in her life,
even with a different husband. Okay, so three different opinions, we'll see
more about that tomorrow.